In this lesson we're going to be exploring static properties and methods in TypeScript,
and these are class members that belong to the class itself, but not to any instance.
We're going to learn how to define static members, when to use them, and how to differ from
instance members. So first of all, what exactly are static members? So static members are attached
to the class itself, but not to any objects that are created from it. And we access them
using the class name, not the keywords at this. So let's do an example. So let's have a class
of the math, utils. I'm going to have a static property called pi, which is 3.14159.
Now I'm going to have a static method, so it's not just properties themselves,
that could be declared as static. We can also have static methods. So let's do static square.
This is going to receive a number, as a parameter, and it's going to return a number.
Let's simply going to do x times x. So how do we access this directly? Let's do a console log.
Now we're going to console log mathitils.py. So notice we don't create a new instance of this
particular class when they're static. We can just simply call mathitils.py, and we're going to do
another console log. Let's say mathitils.square. So this is a static method this time, and we're going
to square the number five. So now we can execute this, we'll run it, and we get our response
over here, 3.14159 blah blah blah, and the answer to our square, 25. So let's do a comparison
between instance members and static members. So I'm going to build a class called counter,
and we're going to define first of all a static member. So static count, let's set that to zero,
and we're going to define a member, which is an instance member. So we don't use the static keyword,
let's going to be type number. We now need to have a constructor because this is complaining
because we need to specify it. So let's just do this dot ID, and it's going to start off at plus plus
our actual class. So counter whoops counter dot count. So notice the sort of slightly strange syntax
here, we're actually just referring to our class name itself counter, and that means we can access
any static properties, which of course this case is count. And all we're doing here is we're just
taking that value and increasing it by one. So the ID is going to start off as one here.
And now we can create an instance of our classroom to const a was new counter. If we do a console log
a dot ID, let's just run that, we get one here, it's going to clear the screen,
get a equals one. And if we do another instance, so if we do const b equals new counter,
and we do a console log b dot ID, let's just clear the screen again, run this, we can see we
now get an ID of two, because this is creating as a static class. So the actual count, when it's
been instigated, when it's been actually created, because of the constructor, we're actually taking
the previous value of count and adding one to it. So this of course is one, and then we have a second
of two. So what we're doing here is we're building what's known as a singleton. So a singleton
allows us to share in an actual single instance of a class, and we can call it multiple times, so we can
access that single member, in this case, count. So in real life, we could build maybe a singleton
as a database access class, where we have a singleton property to be able to access the database
or perhaps a connection string. But other examples could be maybe we have some utility functions,
perhaps math dot max is a classic example, but we also allow a singleton to be able to allow us
to have shared constants, perhaps a config, like config default timeouts, for example, or maybe a
factory methods, like we're just trying to have a class called user, and maybe a method called
create guests. Let's also use for things like global counters registries. And let's actually build
up an example. Let's build up that one about the user, so we could have a class of user,
and we're going to have a constructor, we're going to have a parameter called name, and we're going
to use this short hand this time. Let's actually say it's public, and also going to have another
parameter of is guest. That's going to be simple Boolean, and we're going to have a static method
called create guest. So we're kind of building a factory method here, which is going to return a user,
and are simply return a new user of name of guest, default is guest property to true.
Now if we come to here, and we do as a const guest, one equals user, create guest,
we're now automatically going to get our property guest, assign to one to do console, log
guest one is guest. Let's just clear the screen, execute that, and we get the answer true.
So the static methods are perfect for building things like factories, and we've got an example
here where we have a factory method, which is this case of the create guest, which allows us to
encapsulate creation logic, as well as returning preconfigured instances, our preconfigured instance,
in this case, is we have card coded or specify the is guest property to return true via the factory
You met it.